<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="abstract"> 
    <p>
        The objective of the present dissertation is a born-digital critical edition of the Old Testament book of Qohelet. The edition is based on an
        extensive collation of variant readings from indirect sources – the Septuagint, the Peshitta, the works of <abbr>St.</abbr> Jerome (the Vulgate and the
        Commentary), and the Targum – as well as from direct sources such as the Qumran fragments and Hebrew medieval manuscripts. 
    </p>
    <p>
        The ultimate goal of
        the edition is (a) to reproduce the earliest textual form, the Archetype, that can be reconstructed on the basis of the available evidence; and
        (b) to propose a rehabilitation of the Original writing of the author by resorting, when necessary, to conjectural emendation. We date the
        Archetype to the II century <abbr>BCE</abbr>, corresponding to the date of Hebrew fragments from Qumran, while we place the Original between the 5th and
        3rd centuries <abbr>BCE</abbr>.
    </p>
    <p>
        Unlike previous critical editions of Qohelet, ours follows the so-called eclectic model, which involves the reconstitution of
        a critical text and the preparation of a critical apparatus of secondary variants. Our edition includes, moreover, new data, taken both from
        primary literature, such as the recently published Göttingen Septuagint, and from up-to-date studies and critical commentaries on the text of
        Qohelet.
    </p>
    <p>
        The work is made up of four main parts: an introduction, which sets forth the rationale of the edition and the methodology adopted; the
        collation, where the variants are listed in their original language and extensively discussed; the critical text and the apparatus, with a
        selection of authentic Hebrew variants from the collation; and finally, a translation of the critical text. The edition uses the mark-up language
        of the Text Encoding Initiative (TEI), and will be available both in printed form, via <abbr>LATEX</abbr>, and in digital form, via the TEI-Publisher editor.
    </p>
</div>
